Guide to the Ann Barr Snitow papers, 1950s-2019 RL.01226
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ann Barr Snitow papers
1950s-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Snitow, Ann Barr, 1943-
RL.01226
88 Linear Feet
Ann Barr Snitow was a feminist activist, writer, and professor of literature and gender studies at Eugene Lang College The New School for Liberal Arts. The collection includes teaching files, subject files, materials documenting Snitow's involvement in various feminist activist groups and organizations, Greenham Common Women's Peace Camp, her work with Ellen Willis, feminist publications in Eastern European languages, writings, speeches, correspondence, interviews, Carol Jacobsen films, and recordings of Snitow's feminist radio shows on WBAI in New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Ann Barr Snitow papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2011, 2016-2017, 2019, and 2020.
Biographical Note
Ann Barr Snitow (1943-2019) was a feminist activist, writer, and professor of literature and gender studies at Eugene Lang College The New School for Liberal Arts. She was born in New York and graduated with a literature degree from Cornell in 1965. After pursuing doctoral studies in London, she returned to New York in 1969 and became involved with the feminist movement. In the early 1970s, she hosted the radio show Womankind on the WBAI. She began her teaching career in the Gender Studies department at Rutgers in 1972, where she spent ten years before leaving for The New School. From 1981-1992, she directed the monthly seminar Sex, Gender, and Consumer Culture at the New York Institute for the Humanities. Snitow taught and researched in Poland from the 1980s-2019.
Snitow was one of the founding members of many feminist activist groups including the New York Radical Feminists (1969), Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterlization Abuse (1977), No More Nice Girls (1981), Feminist Anti-Censorship Task Force (1984), Network of East-West Women (1991), with Katha Pollitt and Ellen Willis, and Take Back the Future (2002).
Among her publications, Snitow co/authored or co/edited the books Radical Feminism (1973), Powers of Desire: The Politics of Sexuality (1983), The Feminist Memoir Project: Voices from Women's Liberation (1998), The Feminism of Uncertainty: A Gender Diary (Duke Press, 2015), and Visitors: An American Feminist in East Central Europe (2020).
Related Material
For related materials, see The New York Radical Feminists Records in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Inventory of the New York Radical Feminists Records, 1970-2011
Collection Overview
Collection includes Snitow's teaching files and materials with an emphasis on her work in Eastern Europe, career files, research files, speeches, correspondence, diaries, journals, notebooks, subject files, materials documenting Snitow's involvement in various activist groups and organizations, feminist publications in Eastern European languages, Snitow's writings and publications, published and unpublished materials documenting women's studies, feminist theory and feminist movements, recorded interviews, Snitow's recorded speeches, recordings of Snitow's radio shows on WBAI, and films by feminist documentarian Carol Jacobsen.
Feminism -- Eastern Europe; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Feminism -- Periodicals; Feminism -- Poland; Feminism -- Study and teaching -- United States; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women -- Sexual behavior -- History; Women -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women's rights -- United States -- History; Audio recordings.; Audiovisual materials; Audiocassettes; Negatives (photographs); Snitow, Ann Barr, 1943-; Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (New York, N.Y.); Eugene Lang College; Greenham Common Women's Peace Camp; Jacobsen, Carol (Artist); New York Radical Feminists; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); Willis, Ellen
- Accession (2011-1027), 1969-2011
  Scope and Contents note
  This accession contains teaching files, subject files, materials documenting Snitow's involvement in various groups and organizations, feminist publications in Eastern European languages, and her writings.
  - Women's Liberation Movement Materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 1-2)
  - WBAI Materials, circa 1970-1973 (Box 3, Box 4)
  - New York Radical Feminists, circa 1969 (Box 4)
  - Radical Teaching (Box 4, Box 5)
  - SDS (Box 5)
  - Clippings About Friends (Box 5)
  - Teaching Materials (Box 6-16)
  - New York Institute Files (Box 17-18)
  - New York Institute Articles (Box 19-20)
  - Barnard Study Group Files and Articles (Box 22)
  - Conferences (Box 23)
  - Feminist Anti-Censorship Taskforce (FACT) (Box 24)
  - FACT and Feminists for Free Expression, 3 audiocassettes (Box 25)
  - FACT Articles (Box 26)
  - No More Nice Girls (Box 27)
  - Pornography Articles (Box 28)
  - Feminist Memoir Project Files (co-edited by Snitow) (Box 29)
  - Goals of the Group audiocassettes, 1972 (Box 29)
  - Kracow Course Packs (Box 30, Box 31)
  - Writings by Others (Box 31)
  - Subject files, A-C (Box 32)
  - Subject files, C-P (Box 33)
  - Subject files, P-S (Box 34)
  - Subject files, T-W (Box 35)
  - Changing Love (Snitow writing project) (Box 36-40)
  - Rutgers case, with audiocassettes in box 44 (Box 41-44)
  - Ann Snitow writings (Box 45-46)
  - Publications related to feminism in Eastern Europe in English and Eastern European languages (Box 47-49)
  - WBAI reel-to-reel tapes, original copies, circa 1970-1973 (Box 50-53b)
  - WBAI audiocassettes, original copies, circa 1970-1973 (Box 54-55)
  - reformatted WBAI reel-to-reel tapes (Box 56-57)
- Accession (2019-0134), 1950-2016
  Scope and Contents
  Addition contains teaching material, career files, research and writing, activism, diaries, journals, and notebooks, and recorded interviews.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection contains fragile audiovisual formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - Diaries and Notebooks (Box 58)
  - Teaching in Arthur Kill prison, 2010; 11 folders (Box 59)
  - Carol Vance, 1972-2004; undated; 6 folders (Box 59, Box 60)
  - Archives, 1960s; 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Negatives and Contact Sheets, 1982-1986; 1 items 1 binder (Box 60)
  - Teaching Materials (Box 60)
  - 1950s (Box 60)
  - Eastern European Talks, 2011; 2016; 2 folders (Box 60, Box 61)
  - Network of East/West Women, 2016; 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Talks, 1997; 2011; undated; 7 folders (Box 61)
  - Dorothy Dinnerstein, 1960s-2000s; 12 folders (Box 61)
  - Ellen Willis, 1969-1983 (Box 61)
  - Ellen Willis, 1970s-2010s; 5 folders (Box 62)
  - Greenham part one, 1984-1987; 11 folders (Box 62)
  - Greenham part one, 1980s; 8 folders (Box 63)
  - Talks, 1993-2014; 37 folders (Box 63)
  - Talks, 1996-2011; 14 folders (Box 64)
  - Take Back the Future, 2000s; 6 folders (Box 64)
  - Gender Diary, 1970s-1980s; 14 folders (Box 65, Box 66)
  - Papers, Diaries, Notebooks, 1960s-1970s; 10 folders (Box 66, Box 69)
  - D. Dinnerstein, 1968-1996; 9 folders (Box 66, Box 67)
  - Writings by Ann Barr Snitow, 1987-2013 (Box 67)
  - Greenham (Box 67)
    Includes a CD
  - Course Materials, 1988-1990 (Box 68)
  - Career, Promotion, Re-appointment Files, 1996-2005; 13 folders (Box 68)
  - Politics of Reproductive Technologies, Seminars at New School Inc. Donna Hernrarvay, 1980s (Box 69)
    60 cassettes in cases and drawers
- Accession (2020-0071), 1955-2019
  Addition contains teaching materials from Poland and the New School, materials from the Network of East/West Women, a group Snitow co-founded, correspondence, publications, research, subject files,
  Original audiovisual materials need reformatting before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - Personal Essay Teaching Materials, 1955-2016 (Box 70)
  - A Gender Diary Twenty Years Later, 2010; 4 copies (Box 70)
  - eFKa Women's Foundation Visitors Background Reading, Correspondence, and Interviews, 1997-2013 (Box 71)
  - Cracow Course Materials, 1992-2008 (Box 71, Box 72, Box 73)
  - Carol Jacobsen Films: Censorious, Segregation Unit, Barred and Gagged, From One Prison, 1999-2006; Tapes (Box 71)
  - Network of East West Women (NEWW) Reports, Publications, 1996-2013 (Box 72, Box 74)
  - NEWW Library of Publications in Central and Eastern European Languages Collected by Snitow (Box 72, Box 73, Box 74)
  - Caught Looking: Feminism, Pornography, and Censorship, 2002 (Box 73)
  - Promotion Review Packet, A. Snitow, 2011 (Box 73)
  - Cracow Notebooks, 1992-2011 (Box 74)
  - NEWW Grant Application Files (Box 74)
  - Correspondence (Box 74)
  - Cracow Course Materials, 1995-2007 (Box 75, Box 77)
  - Cracow Student Papers, 1995-2008 (Box 75)
  - Gender Montage: Paradigms in Post Soviet Space, 2001-2003; 9 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Roe v. Wade at Twenty Five: Blackmun Lecture on Privacy, 1998; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Selfloving: Portrait of a Women's Sexuality Seminar (Betty Dodson), 1993; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Working Girls, 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Candida Royalle Presents Three Daughters, 1986; VHS (Box 76)
  - Ann Snitow in Krakow, VHS (Box 76)
  - Drakulic Talk I and II, VHS (Box 76)
  - UM Law School Conference on Prostitution, 1992; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Veteran Feminists Event, 13 December 1997; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - Women's Studies: Eastern Europe, 1994; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - My Road to Feminism, 1 VHS cassettes (Box 76)
  - My Talk at DIA re: No More Nice Girls, June, 1989; VHS (Box 76)
  - Interview, Kracow part 2, 2004; Audiocassette (Box 76)
  - FSG Women's Group CR, 1982; 1 audiocassettes (Box 76)
  - Greenham Common, 1982-1985; 44 slides (Box 76)
  - Window Peace Performance, December, 1986; 36 slides (Box 76)
  - Silver Linings Playbook, 2012; DVD (Box 76)
  - Gender Syllabi, 1989-2009 (Box 76)
  - Writings and Talks by A. Snitow, 1981-2014 (Box 76, Box 79)
  - Correspondence, 1971-2019 (Box 76, Box 77, Box 80)
  - Articles and Talks by A. Snitow (Box 77)
  - Take Back the Future, circa 2002 (Box 77)
  - NEWW Documents, 2004 (Box 77)
  - Occupy Wall Street, circa 2011 (Box 77)
  - New School Program Development Notes (Box 77)
  - NEWW Membership Directory (Box 77)
  - Feminists for Clinton, 2008 (Box 77)
  - Drafts of Visitors (Box 77)
  - Visitors Files (Box 78)
  - ECE Teaching Seminars (Box 78)
  - Notes, Notebooks, Drafts (Box 79)
  - Examples of Student Work from Introduction to Feminist Thought and Action Course (New School) (Box 79)
  - Simms Taback (Box 80)
  - Feminist Memoir Project (Box 80)
  - Notes, Research Material (Box 80)
  - Eva Charkiewicz (Box 80)
  - Poland, 2016 (Box 80)
  - NEWW Files (Box 80, Box 82)
  - Austria Diaries, 1999 (Box 80)
  - Gender Studies: East Central Europe (Box 80)
  - Feminist Studies: East Central Europe (Box 80)
  - Letters: Eastern Europe (Box 80)
  - Theories of Gender Studies (Box 80)
  - Barrie Karp (Box 80)
  - Gender Studies Course Descriptions, 2006 (Box 80)
  - Get Well Cards, Letters (Box 80)
  - Association for Women in Slavic Studies (AWSS) Outstanding Achievement Award, 2017 (Box 80)
  - Essay on My Political History (Box 80)
  - Strategy Actions (wall post-it notes) (Box 80)
  - Abortion and International Human Rights, 2004-2005 (Box 81)
  - OSI Summer School, Albania, 2004 (Box 81)
  - Krakow Summer Working Copies, 2008-2009 (Box 81)
  - Crisis Files, 2011 (Box 81)
  - Recordings of NEWW Meetings (including founding), 1991-1995; 13 audiocassettes (Box 82)
    Contains fragile audiovisual format that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - NEWW: Status of Women in New Market Economies Conference, 1 VHS cassettes (Box 82)
  - NEWW New York Event, 1 DVDs (Box 82)
  - Breaking the Silence US version, 1 DVDs (Box 82)
  - NEWW Early Development Files (Box 82)
  - Calendars, 1963-1964 (Box 82)
  - Cultural Studies Notes, Course Material (Box 83)
  - The Barnard Occasional Papers on Women's Issues vol. IV, no. 1, 1989 (Box 83)
  - Feminism of Uncertainty: cut pieces, publicity, and reviews, circa 2015 (Box 83)
  - Dorothy Notes, 1991 (Box 83)
  - Adam Puchejda Interview, 2011 (Box 83)
  - Holocaust Book, 2016 (Box 83)
  - Great Barrier Reef, 2017 (Box 83)
  - Letter for New York Magazine, February, 2017 (Box 83)
  - New School Workshop on Strategies, 2017 (Box 83)
  - Backlash/Signs, 2018 (Box 83)
  - #MeToo, circa 2006-2019 (Box 83)
  - Nation Interviews (Box 84)
  - Transcript of Oral History with A. Snitow at the New School, 2014 (Box 84)
  - Speculative Fictions (Box 84)
  - Bard (Box 84)
  - Columbia (Box 84)
  - Fulbright Specialist-Current (Box 84)
  - Karolina Kopek-China (Box 84)
  - Warsaw Summer School, 2012 (Box 84)
  - Krakow, 1992-1993 (Box 84)
  - Boycott, Divestment, Sanctions (BDS) Movement/Salaita Talk (Box 84)
  - Veronica Perera (Box 84)
  - Papers from Women and Security Seminar, 2002 (Box 84)
  - Third Wave Feminism (Box 84)
  - Religious/Secular (Box 85)
  - Post-Humansim (Box 85)
  - Politically Correct (Box 85)
  - Public and Private (Box 85)
  - Freud (Box 84)
  - Muslim Women/EU (Box 85)
  - EU (Box 85)
  - Bullying (Box 85)
  - The Care Crisis (Box 85)
  - Architecture and Feminism (Box 85)
  - Archiving (Box 85)
  - Anorexia (Box 85)
  - New Feminist Theory (Box 85)
  - Trafficking (Box 85)
  - Women and Work (Box 85)
  - War (Box 85)
  - Violence Against Women (Box 85)
  - Sex Wars Aftermath (Box 85)
  - Medicalization of Sexuality (Box 85)
  - Marriage (Box 85)
  - Jeff Goldfarb (Box 86)
  - Elzbieta Matynia (Box 86)
  - Harvard Talk, 1996 (Box 86)
  - Talks/Handwritten Notes (Box 86)
  - Polish Abortion (Box 86)
  - Gift/Guilt (Box 86)
  - Nanette Funk (Box 86)
  - Memories of the Meeting (Box 86)
  - The List (Box 86)
  - Visitors Background Documents (Box 86)
  - Slawka Chapter Draft Visitors (Box 87)
  - Internationalism Notes and Drafts for Visitors (Box 87)
  - Czech Chapter Background Visitors (Box 87)
  - Czech Notes (Box 87)
  - John Fetter Interview for Gosia used in Visitors (Box 87)
  - Notes on Roma, Online Project, Fullness of Life for Visitors (Box 87)
  - Poem by Jennifer Firestone for A. Snitow (Box 87)
  - Course Readers, 10 folders (Box 87, Box 88)
  - NEWW Board of Directors Meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 88)
  - NEWW: Structure (Box 88)
  - Matsunaga (Box 88)
  - Retirement Talk, April 2019 (Box 88)
  - No Longer in Exile, March, 2010 (Box 88)
  - Nation Interview (Box 88)
  - Emeritus Letter, 2019 (Box 88)
  - Interview with High Heels, May, 2018 (Box 88)
  - Holocaust Piece (Box 88)
  - Poland Final Reports, June, 2016 (Box 88)
  - Dissent Piece, 2018 (Box 88)
  - One Hundred Years - Women's Time Talk, 2018 (Box 88)
  - Flexible Orchestra Talk, 2018 (Box 88)
  - Teaching in Jeff's Class, 2017 (Box 88)
  - Memoir Readings (Box 88)
  - Letter from Johns Hopkins Professor Discriminating Against Women, 1969 (Box 88)
  - Liana Jakeli: Codes and Verses, 2006; DVD (Box 89)
  - Liana Jakeli: I Don't Know, VHS (Box 89)
  - Liana Jakeli: Invisible, 2003; DVD (Box 89)
  - Liana Jakeli: To Be a Worth Woman (Box 89)
  - Where are You, My Suliko, DVD (Box 89)
  - Notebooks, 1972-2008 (Box 89)
  - SCUM Manifesto, circa 1968; 2 copies (Box 89)
  - Caught Looking (working copies), circa 1988; 3 copies (Box 89)
  - Diary of a Conference on Sexuality (one working copy), 1982 (Box 89)
  - Heresies Sex Issue #12, 1981 (Box 89)
  - Conditions: #1, 10, 11/12, 14-17, 1976-1990 (Box 89)
  - Quest: A Feminist Quarterly: vol. IV no. 4; vol. V no. 2-4, 1977-1978 (Box 89)
  - NEWW mousepad (Box 89)
  - Writings, Notes, Correspondence, 1991-1995 (Box 90)
  - Livingston College Publications for Students, 1971-1979 (Box 90)
  - Dinnerstein Student (Box 90)
  - Women's Groups and Feminist Recordings, 1977-1987; 40 audiocassettes (Box 90)
  - Ann Snitow in Conversation with Victoria Hattam, September 24 and 27, 2014; DVD (Box 90)
  - Full Sequence of Ann Snitow Interview, Flash Drives (Box 90)
    Contains electronic records that may need to be reformatted. Access copies of electronic records must be accessed in our reading room.
  - Cracow Course Readers, 14 folders (Box 91, Box 92)
  - East Central Europe (ECE) talks by A. Snow (Box 92)
  - ECE Women's Group Fliers and Publications (Box 92)
  - Krakow - Why Are We Afraid of Gender Talk, 2015 (Box 92)
  - Poland: Roma's Interview with Gay Men on Feminism, May-June, 2015 (Box 92)
  - John Feffer Interview with A. Snitow, 2014 (Box 92)
  - Background for Archive Section of the Feminism of Uncertainty, circa 2015 (Box 92)
  - Notebook, 2008 (Box 93)
  - Ann and Dan's Wedding Photographs, 1 cdrs (Box 93)
  - Syllabi and Materials/notes/lectures on Political Sensorium and the Left (Box 93)
  - Fulbright Specialists Award-Albania, March, 2011 (Box 93)
  - Trans*Fesitival Talk, 2015 (Box 93)
  - Albania Course, 2011 (Box 93)
  - Gdansk Talk, 2004 (Box 93)
  - Association for Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies Roundtable on Anti-Genderism, Women's Organizing, and LGBTQ Rights, 2016 (Box 93)
  - Ministry Talk, Warsaw, 2015 (Box 93)
  - Belgrade Democracy Seminar Talk, 2000 (Box 93)
  - 20th Anniversary Symposium Talk, Transregional Center for Democratic Studies, 1989 (Box 93)
  - General Feminism Talks, 2015 (Box 93)
  - International Project-Women's Memories: Searching for Identity Within Socialism, 2007 (Box 93)
  - Democracy and Diversity (Graduate Institute in Cracow Flyers), 1993-1994 (Box 93)
  - Meredith Tax on the State of the Women's Movement, 2015 (Box 93)
  - Women Pro and Con. Peter Pauper Press, 1958 (Box 93)
  - Taylor, Katheryn. Generations of Denial: 75 Short Biographies of Women in History. Times Change Press, 1971 (Box 93)
  - Morgan, Robin, editor. Sisterhood is Powerful: An Anthology of Writings from the Women's Liberation Movement. Vintage Books, 1970 (Box 93)
  - Gornick, Vivian and Barbara K. Moran. Women in Sexist Society: Studies in Power and Powerlessness. Basic Books, 1971 (Box 93)
  - Schneir, Mirian. Feminism: The Essential Historical Writings. Vintage Books, 1972 (Box 93)
  - Liberation Now: Writings from the Women's Liberation Movement: Dell Publishing, 1971 (Box 93)
  - Stambler, Sookie. Women's Liberation: Blueprint for the Future: Ace Books, 1970 (Box 93)
  - Tanner, Leslie B. Voices From Women's Liberation: Signet, 1970 (Box 93)
  - Cooke, Joanne, et al., editors. The New Women: A Motive Anthology on Women's Liberation: Fawcett Premier, 1970 (Box 93)
  - Rowbotham, Sheila. Women's Liberation and Revolution: A Bibliography: Falling Wall Press, 1973 (Box 94)
  - Kraditor, Aileen S., editor. Up From the Pedestal: Selected Writings in the History of American Feminism: Quadrangle Books, 1968 (Box 94)
  - Martin, Wendy, editor. The American Sisterhood: Writings of the Feminist Movement from Colonial Times to the Present: Harper and Row Publishers, 1972 (Box 94)
  - Hole, Judith, and Ellen Levine. Rebirth of Feminism: Quadrangle Books, 1971 (Box 94)
  - Thompson, Mary Lou, editor. Voices of the New Feminism: Beacon Press, 1970 (Box 94)
  - Building Feminist Theory: Essays from Quest A Feminist Quarterly: Longman, 1981 (Box 94)
  - Koedt, Anne, et al., Radical Feminism. Quadrangle Books, 1973 (Box 94)
  - Edwards, Lee R. et al., editors. Woman: An Issue. Little, Brown, and Company, 1972 (Box 94)
  - Baxandall, Rosalyn and Linda Gordon, editors. Dear Sisters: Dispatches from the Women's Liberation Movement. Basic Books, 2002 (Box 94)
  - Salper, Roberta, editor. Female Liberation: History and Current Politics. Alfred A. Knopf, 1972 (Box 94)
  - Sorell, Walter. Three Women: Lives of Sex & Genius. The Bobs-Merrill Company, 1975 (Box 94)
  - Vance, Carol S. Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality. Pandora, 1989 (Box 94)